

guzmánLópez

biology sciences graduate and IT analyst student

about

30 years Male, Uruguayan ↑ Montevideo, Uruguay

contact

✓ guzilop@gmail.com
✓ @Guzman
★ guzmanlopez

languages

Spanish mother tongue English elemental proficiency

programming

♥ R language (6 yr) JavaScript, HTML5 & CSS (3 yr)

also: SQL (2 yr) ASP.Net with C# (< 1 yr)

03

🐧 Linux (6 yr)

interests

professional: data analysis, programming, research, web app creation, big data, databases, spatial analysis, geographic information systems **personal:** friends, tango dancing (learn and teach), tango music, hiking, free software development, ocean, nature, wildlife, read

education

2015-Now IT Analyst

ORT University - Faculty of Engineering, Montevideo

Courses until now:

Databases II (SQL syntax, queries, triggers) - studying

Programming III (ASP.Net with C#) – studying

Databases I (SQL syntax, queries, ERM) - 82/100 (partially approved, last

exam

Programming II (ASP.Net with C#) – 88/100 (partially approved, last exam) Usability and Accessibility workshop (CSS) – 96/100 (totally approved)

Programming I (JS, HTML) – 100/100 (totally approved) Computing Introduction – 86/100 (totally approved)

2004-2011 **Biology sciences graduate** University of the Republic – Faculty of Sciences, Montevideo

Specialization in Oceanography

Global mark: 9.44

Courses: 23 approved / 23 total

Exams: 26 approved / 24 total (+2 exonerated)

2003 **Bachelor** Pre-University Institute Juan XXIII, Montevideo

Specialization in Agronomy

Mark: 9 1 to 12 (max)

1998-2002 High School Student

Pallotti High School, Montevideo

Specialization in Biology

Marks: 12 (1998) – 12 (1999) – 11 (2000) – 12 (2001) – 11 (2002) 1 to 12 (max)

experience

2014-Now National Direction of Aquatic Resources (DINARA)

Montevideo, Uruguay

Hydroacoustic consultant

Acquisition, processing, visualization and analysis of scientific echosounder

and sonar data.

2013 **Project: FREPLATA II (PNUD - GEF)**

Montevideo, Uruguay

Oceanographic data management assistant

Organization, systematization and analysis of historical and new generated data relating to meteorological and oceanographic variables.

2010-2012 **Project: Fisheries Management in Uruguay (DINARA - FA0)** Montevideo, Uruguay **Hydroacoustic consultant specialist**

Acquisition, processing, visualization and analysis of scientific echosounder and sonar data.

2009 Subprojects: Whitemouth croaker and Argentine hake (FAO - Ricaldoni Foundation)

Montevideo, Uruguay

Hydroacoustic technical support

Acquisition, processing, visualization and analysis of scientific echosounder data from Argentine hake and Whitemouth croaker fish abundance assessment surveys abroad research vessel "Aldebarán".

2008 National Direction of Aquatic Resources (DINARA)

Montevideo, Uruguay

Hydroacoustic collaborator.

Help acquiring, processing and visualizing acoustic data from the research survey: "Assessment of the Hawkfish by means of hydroacoustic methods and classic swap area in the Uruguayan Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ)", abroad the research vessel "Aldebarán".

research

2007-Now Activities:

- +25 research reports
- +15 research surveys abroad different vessels
- 13 complementary courses
- 7 communication instances (oral presentations and posters)
- 4 different teaching instances
- 3 peer-reviewed co-author articles
- 2 student research projects

complementary courses

most important

2014	Introduction to databases analysis using R Approved: without mark	University of the Republic - Course
2014	Linux network administration Mark: 100/100	Linux Center - Course
2011	Introduction to R language programming Approved: without mark	University of the Republic - Course
2009	Effective publication of scientific information Approved: without mark	UNESCO - Course

publications

most important

articles in peer-reviewed journals

Management and research on plastic debris in Uruguayan Aquatic Systems: update and perspectives

Juan Pablo Lozoya, Alvar Carranza, Javier Lenzi, Emanuel Machín, Franco Teixeira de Mello, Silvana González, Daniel Hernández, Gissell Lacerot, Gastón Martínez, Fabrizio Scarabino, José Sciandro, Gabriela Vélez-Rubio, Fernanda Burgues, Daniel Carrizo, Felipe Cedrés, Julio Chocca, Daniel de Álava, Sebastián Jiménez, Valentina Leoni, Pablo Limongi, Guzmán López, Yamilia Olivera, Mariana Pereira, Luis Rubio, Federico Weisntein

Revista de Gestão Costeira Integrada 15.3 (Aug. 2015) pp. 377-393. 2015

Hydrodynamic and geomorphological controls on surface sedimentation at the Subtropical Shelf Front / Brazil–Malvinas Confluence transition off Uruguay (Southwestern Atlantic Continental Margin)

P. Franco-Fraguas, L. Burone, M. Mahiques, L. Ortega, C. Urien, A. Muñoz, G. López, Y. Marin, A. Carranza, N. Lahuerta, C. Mello

Marine Geology 349 (Mar. 2014) pp. 24-36. 2014

Deep-water coral reefs from the Uruguayan outer shelf and slope

GRUPO MIGUEL OLIVER URUGUAY 0110, Alvar Carranza, Araceli Muñoz Recio, Marcelo Kitahara, Fabrizio Scarabino, Leonardo Ortega, Guzmán López, Paula Franco-Fraguas, Camila Mello, Juan Acosta, Antia Fontan

Marine Biodiversity 42.3 (Sept. 2012) pp. 411-414. 2012

reports

Hydroacoustic assessment in Santa Lucía River (Uruguay).

Guzmán López, Gerardo Rodríguez, Diego Pagano, Juana Fernández, Leonardo Ortega *Research report, 2016*

ER60 EK-60 SIMRAD echosounder's software guide.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2015

Interactive map of artisanal fishing zones and artisanal ports in Uruguay.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2015

Web application to extract, convert and visualize Tritech StarFish 990F Side Scan Sonar navigation.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2015

Hydroacoustic assessment in Noboa reservoir (Salto, Uruguay).

Guzmán López, Silvana González, Julio Chocca, Bernardo González, Rosanna Foti *Research report, 2015*

Configuration and maintenance of the EK-60 SIMRAD echosounder's local network in the research vessel "Aldebarán".

Guzmán López, Gerardo Martínez

Technical report, 2015

Assessment of seismic prospection activity in the continental shelf of Uruguay.

Luis Rubio, Silvana González, Guzmán López, Claudio Berriolo, Sebastián Jiménez, Javier Lenzi, Andrés Domingo

Research report, 2015

"Ema" web application.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2013

Guidelines for an oceanographic database.

Guzmán López

Technical report, 2013

"MODIS" web application.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2013

"Pampero" web application.

Guzmán López

Software user guide, 2013